this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
I see radio brings you relevant the
detailed discussions about software
engineering topics at least once a month
thanks to our audience and the partners
listed on our website for supporting the
podcast
[Music]
welcome listeners to another episode of
software engineering radio we are
recording this one at the IOP or
conference in Munich Germany in January
2011 and we were sitting in in a room
that's intended to be used as a quiet
area so there might be other people
coming in and being as quiet as we are I
hope they won't disturb too much anyway
our guest today is Andrew Brown served
from ei and I guess you want to
introduce yourself first hello
I work for Electronic Arts and I have
worked for that company for
approximately 21 years now and we're in
the video game industry and we do titles
such as FIFA soccer
Need for Speed battlefield and a variety
of other titles in a variety of genres
we're a worldcat worldwide company and
I'm a senior software engineer in the
Vancouver Canada studio mm-hmm so I
guess it's obvious now what the topic is
going to be for this episode we're going
to talk about game architecture and the
kinds of games I'm not sure if everybody
knows what these title actually
represent but these are let's say action
games racing games so can you
characterize these kinds of games a
little bit so differentiating them from
let's say SimCity or something you know
is there a way of characterizing the
kind of games you build well ea actually
owns Maxis as well so we do SimCity and
The Sims and our sports label games our
stadium based baseball football American
football and a variety of other titles
and that typically the player is in
control of a whole team and you can
switch between individuals on the team
and get a 3d view and controlled player
as the player runs around and actually
plays the game and scores goals
hopefully or whatever else you do in the
sport
then we also have titles like
battlefield or battlefield 1942 or
Battlefield Bad Company and these are
more in the what we call the
first-person shooter genre and they're
usually set in wartime or some science
fiction genre and you find weapons and
try to achieve mission objectives we
also have the Need for Speed line which
I've been personally involved in for the
past several years and that's racing
games and sometimes they are strength
sanctioned street racing and sometimes
they are sort of more illicit and
there's a storyline involved generally
and you know you're an undercover police
officer or something trying to to break
into the mob or something of that le yeh
has other games like the Lord of the
Rings series which is sort of a fantasy
role-playing or a what's called a RTS
real time simulation and it's sort of
multiple sides fighting epic battles we
have also done the Harry Potter series
and games like dead space which is sort
of a dark horror adventure kind of genre
so quite a variety and and I guess since
you are mostly involved with the Need
for Speed franchise of series I guess
most of the things we're going to talk
about kind of have a background in this
kind of game so if you don't say
anything else we basically talk about
racing games in some sense although the
concepts of course are applicable to the
others as well but that's your
background yeah my background in the
last couple of years has been knee for
speed and we also did a skateboarding
product right skate yeah okay so if we
look at these racing games can you give
us I mean maybe you should some say one
more thing you did a keynote yesterday
about this topic and I saw the keynote
so I might I might kind of implicitly
reference things that are saw in the
keynote
so one thing you showed was how these
kinds of games have evolved over the
last whatever 20 years from the
pixelated you know beginning of the 90s
to what we have today can you give us a
little bit of a you know kind of
timeline regarding I don't know screen
resolution level of detail how these
things changed
sure the the state of affairs when I
joined the game industry in 1990 was
that the screen resolutions were
approximately 320 pixels wide by 200
tall and to give you some idea on a
typical TV or display you'd be looking
at it and you almost have to use your
imagination to realize that this thing
in the distance is a car I mean it is
very vague and blocky and
the number of colors we could draw you
know in the beginning was on the
Macintosh for example it was black and
white and on on the PC some of the
displays only had 16 colors per pixel so
the the range of colors we could show
was very very limited and the
computational capability of the
computers was so limited we couldn't do
even 3d graphics and so we would have
pre drawn 2d sprites that we would draw
on the screen in the correct position
and when the car got car got farther
away we would actually switch to a
different texture that was drawn to be
smaller and tricks like that and so the
whole thing was an illusion of 2d layers
displayed on this low resolution screen
and the audio was was little better than
blips and Boop's and then shortly
thereafter as machines started to become
faster and heavier duty math became
possible screen resolutions slowly
started to increase we moved to 3d and
then a little while later screen
resolutions jumped up VGA arrived on the
screen and we were then up to 640 by 480
and we usually had enough compute power
that we could run at 20 frames per
second and once you get to 20 frames per
second now you start to perceive real
motion previously at 10 frames per
second it was pretty chunky and you
really had to use your imagination as
you get the 20 and then hopefully 30
frames per second as you know movies or
after for 4 frames per second and that
is sort of the threshold of where you
can see continuous motion and actually
the the human perception you can you can
perceive smooth motion all the way up to
around 60 frames per se
I can because if I go to the movies and
I can see that I watch 24 frames film
and you see rapid movement I think I
perceive in canoeing continuities it
kind of feels it looks junky a little
bit or is that my imagination no you're
absolutely correct as big pans and stuff
like that happened you can definitely
perceive right at the edge of your
perception and even the TV speed of well
in North American TV speed to 30 frames
per second it looks smooth but when you
see a 30 frame per second game versus a
60 frames per second game there is a
clear difference to most people some
people have a hard time perceiving it
we're all a bit different in our visual
acuity but 60 frames per second is
pretty rock-solid smooth for most people
mm-hmm so that's what you're shooting
for today so these days there's a
trade-off and usually a game particular
game has to make a decision so
resolutions have gone now far beyond the
640 by 480 and at high definition
television resolution we talked about
the number of vertical lines and so
we've gone from 480 to 720p and now to
1080p and the frame rates of the TV is
60 frames per second or higher some of
them display higher but we generally can
only send a new image to the TV at 60
Hertz and the game has to make a choice
because 60 looks a bit smoother but it's
pretty subtle effect 30 looks almost as
smooth and if you have twice as much
time to render the frame of the game you
can get twice as much detail into a
single frame so the actual picture might
look better but you get fewer of them
exactly so it's a trade-off between
smooth motion versus quality of the
image okay quite often games will choose
quality the image and it really comes
down to a gameplay choice like some
games play better at 60 Hertz actually I
saw during the keynote yesterday you you
gave a little demo of the need for speed
shift I think it was called it's great
and I have to say I don't follow games
that much except for Angry Birds I guess
and flight simulator
but that was pretty impressive I mean it
it really the level of detail that went
into the rendering especially I mean all
these different shades and you showed
this once live with you know scratches
on the on the car and stuff so this was
it was really impressive so so if you
listener haven't played one of these
games recently try to I don't know go to
youtube and look at one of them make
sure it's a HD resolution it's pretty
impressive so um anyway so we're going
to talk about these kinds of games and I
guess we we're going to talk about two
or three aspects one is that the
ingredients so what goes into building
one of these games like you know
simulation rendering audio things like
that and then we're going to look at
some of the more current challenges
you're looking at which is concurrency
and in multi-platform and then you have
identified a bunch of patterns that you
use when building these systems we're
going to talk about some of these so
let's start with some of the ingredients
and I guess the base is for a game like
Need for Speed shift is obviously the
the simulation that goes on that kind of
decides what happens as opposed to how
its shown and how it's you know ruined
rendered in a visual and audio way so
how do you go about simulating the
physics are exact is it I mean is it
real physics is it all fake it's
definitely not all fake
so underlying the game engine there is a
basic film physics simulation and we
call it a rigidbody simulation and at
that basic level there's objects in the
world and they're modeled with momentum
and they have you know tensors and and
all these other physical concepts and
the simulation is updated at generally
30 or 60 frames per second right and the
physics engine is responsible for taking
the forces that are applied to the
vehicles and any other objects that are
moving around turning those into changes
to the vehicles velocity momentum and
acceleration and then applying gravity
and then detecting when objects collide
together and then generating reasonable
responses when they have these
collisions as well as events like the
noises in the sand that particle effects
so the let's say the math that goes into
simulating this are the real physical
formulas but the level or the way you
have to tune the overall amount of
processing you have to do is basically
the the granularity of the objects is
that is that fair to say or do you
actually do cheats on the on the way you
calculate things so at the rigidbody
level that I mentioned the physics is
actually fairly stable and some EA games
for example use there's a licensable
havoc a product called havoc that is a
physics engine and by it's a piece of
middleware right that you can license
and other games use internal internally
developed physics but the the key point
is at the level of the rigidbody the
physics is pretty much actual real
mechanical physics and Newtonian
mechanics or whatever the place where
the fudging and the tuning and then not
quite real physics comes in is in the
actual simulation of the vehicle and it
really sits on top of the rigid body
physics and it generates forces to move
the the bodies that are the cars so you
don't seem relate the whole engine and
the way that the tires interact with the
pavement this is more or less
approximated the engine is definitely an
approximation we don't simulate the
cylinders or anything like that so we
have curves that we go and we looked at
the manufacturers data curves and we
generate a rough simulation of for a
model of that that's a fairly high-level
model but you mentioned tire physics on
the other hand we actually have quite
sophisticated tire physics models that
do they're not you wouldn't find a
physicist who's working for the
automotive industry facing car design on
these things but we are tuning it
carefully so that it gives the right
feel and it exhibits quite a few of the
attributes the actual real tire physics
exhibit but we don't take it to a next
ride yesterday you said that fun and a
good feeling is more important than
actual complete physical accuracy
absolutely so it's really key that the
player feel like he's driving the real
car and strangely enough trying to
actually accurately reproduce the
numbers that the real cars get on the
track doesn't give that feel right part
of the reason for that is because the
driver the player of the game isn't
sitting in his out es5 or whatever it is
driving around the track feeling the
g-force is moving him holding a steering
wheel unless you have a really right
sophisticated game setup you've got a
little gamepad control on your hands and
through that you are trying to
experience racing around the track so it
takes a fair bit of tuning artistic
license and there is a there's a real
art to defining the feel of a game to
making it feel gritty and aggressive and
at the same time most game players
aren't professional racecar drivers and
we want them to feel successful right so
it is a game first and foremost in
addition to the the car and its
interaction with the road you also have
to simulate things like how does the car
deform if you crash into a wall and if
you accelerate too fast how does the
smoke you know leave the tires and stuff
this is not really real right this is
all this is approximated these kind of
things yeah absolutely
the the damage is designed to return a a
good visual look something that looks
impressive something that doesn't break
the illusion of reality
yeah the suspension of disbelief is a
term we use that the user wants to be in
the game playing and if you see
something that just looks wrong like you
can see through the polygonal model of
the game of the car you don't want to
see that so we carefully deform the
models so that we don't break the
illusion but it still looks like a car
that got seriously crunched in reality
we don't actually do much to the model
of the car so even though the front end
may have been compressed in by six
inches we probably don't actually move
where the collision happens we don't
need to because you can't notice yeah
yeah and and and things like particle
how do you say swarms kind of you know
if you have many small particles that
move together that that's you would use
these swarm kind of algorithms where you
define you know one where you say you
have
primitive rules how the particles
interact with each other and then you
would kind of emerge you know that the
baby hate behavior of the small of the
cloud of the particles would emerge from
the yeah we don't do this for the smoke
probably it's too detailed well actually
it's not true we have we have
specialists who their job is to set up
these particle systems okay and each of
the particle kinds of particle systems
has its own set of rules as you call
them right little algorithms right that
govern the motion of the particles and
smoke is actually a really important one
to get the motion I know we've spent a
great deal of time working out how to
get believable volumetric smoke and
there's different kinds of smoke some
smoke comes out of the tailpipe some
smoke comes off the engine after you
crashed the some of the most important
smoke in a racing game comes off the
wheels yes and it's different whether it
comes off the front wheels the back
wheels all four wheels depending which
which engine which wheels the engine is
driving and so you know smoke actually
curls around the tire as you burn out
and all this stuff has to be modeled and
it's modeled not from physical
correctness point of view but from a
believability point of view and then
it's balanced against the trade-off if
you we can't render an unlimited number
of particles so we have to carefully
design them so that they represent a
reasonable load to render and yet
generate a pleasing effect really yeah
so let's move on to a video presentation
to the optics basically I guess one I
mean one question I could ask initially
I know it's not the case but I can still
ask it is this ray tracing going on it's
this actual simulation of light rays or
what kinds of ways of rendering the
actual scene are used so it's all
polygonal triangle rendering and it's
it's not ray tracing although for some
purposes we will a trace rays although
usually not for graphics strangely
enough however it's a shaded lighting
model in different games used different
techniques so some of the latest games
are using what's called
shading and the idea is you you render
all your triangles into the world scene
and then you apply lights after the fact
on the rendered result traditionally in
older models you would render the
polygons and as you drew each triangle
onto the screen you would figure out the
lights that are shining on that polygon
and color it appropriately
so how do I have to imagine actually
programming this visualization is it
that developers actually let's say draw
pixels or do you have pre prefabricated
pre-rendered sprites as you called it
back in the day do you have certain
patterns that you may be applied to
walls or to the street pre-built or how
do you you know how do you know which
level of granularity do programmers who
implement the visualization algorithm
how detailed do they have to actually
render each pixel how does this work
I have no idea about graphics
programming as you probably can notice
so that's yeah so so what we get from
the art team is 3d models which are
essentially a cloud of vertices in 3d
space and these vertices are connected
by edges which form triangles and
applied to these triangles is a bunch of
properties so lighting information or
specular information there's a variety
of different properties that describe
that the triangle and there's a
generally a texture sometimes quite
often a whole layer of textures some of
which are simply the the 2d visual image
that you would see if you are looking at
that part so you can imagine a brick
wall and it essentially is a photograph
of a brick wall and that is drawn onto
the triangle some of the textures are
are not directly physical
representations things like a bump map
will affect how light reflects off the
texture so it defines shape so that we
can then on-the-fly calculate how that
surfaces are interacting
the lights that happen to be in the
environment so with the textures and the
models that are produced by the artists
these are fed into the rendering engine
and programmers interact with this first
and foremost by marshalling the men off
disk into main memory and then arranging
for them to get to the GPU so that the
graphics processor can actually use that
data and then they are fed into the
graphics processor along with what are
called shader programs and there's
generally two kinds of shader programs
there are new kinds coming
but first what runs on the program on
the GPU is called the vertex shader so
every vertex in a triangle is made of
three vertices the three corners
every vertex gets processed by this
vertex shader program and it does things
like takes its the vertices position in
3-space and works out where that's going
to get projected on to on the screen and
it's going to calculate normal which is
the perpendicular to the triangle in
various other parameters and these are
then passed along to the second program
which is called the pixel shader and the
pixel shader gets the inputs from the
triangle and that those are generated by
the vertex shader and a triangle as
three of them and what the hardware does
is it interpolates from one vertex to
the other along the edge and so you get
an array of pixels once it's a
rasterized onto the the frame buffer
yeah so so one thing may be that most
people probably know is that the
abstractions you work with on the GPU
really isn't a pixel it's it's these
triangles and there are layers and there
are all kinds of 3d magic going on on
the GPU itself right so there's not just
pixel processing yeah there's both the
vertices get processed and then the GPU
does this interpolation magic and it
works out exactly which pixels go into
it and then it runs the pixel shader to
actually calculate the color that it
wants for output at the background so um
GPUs are actually quite sophisticated
today as many of our listeners probably
know how much of the work of the overall
rendering is done on the CPU and how
what's the work share between the two
well that would depend on how you
measure it I would say that probably 90%
or more of the computation is happening
on the GPU the vast majority of it what
the CPU is doing is figuring out what to
draw and importantly what not to draw
and then submitting all of that to the
GPU in the form the GPU can can deal
with and the CPU ideally never actually
touches each vertex and never actually
touches each texture now there are
exceptions to that especially on a
machine like the PlayStation 3 where
there is a lot more computational
capability in the CPUs because then we
want to load balance between the two so
we'll move some of the calculations over
onto the CPU but fundamentally the GPU
is doing all the work on the vertices in
the pixel mm-hm
um how do you program GPUs can you write
C code and run them on the GPU or how I
mean it's obviously if they're they
these things are highly parallelized so
right you have to have certainly
parallel algorithms we also have
specialized languages for that or is it
is it C++ well it's definitely not C++
so when you're programming graphics
problems you're either running DirectX
or you're running OpenGL right yeah
in DirectX there's a language called
HLSL which stands for high-level shading
language and it is a very C like
language that's been extended to have
very common graphics primitives so float
fours for example is a type in the
language and there's a bunch of built-in
functions that are commonly used for
doing graphics calculations dot products
and stuff like that and so it's a
language carefully tuned to do the sort
of calculations that you want to do in
your vertex shader or your pixel shader
and that gets compiled down into native
GPU assembly code basically and in
OpenGL you have GLSL which is graphics
library shader language and it's very
very similar to HLSL okay let's we'll
come back to the to the graphics stuff
and to the challenge of multi-core and
Gen
the parallelization later let's briefly
move on to the audio and yesterday you
mentioned that to render if that's the
right word and the audio the sounds of a
car you had some sometimes have 27
different kinds of sounds that you mix
together to give a you know a good audio
representation so there seems to be
going on more than I thought in the
audio world yeah so I pulled the number
27 out of the air but there are many and
in fact it might be more than twenty
several different components there are
many different elements that go into a
single engines car sound and when you
consider we have multiple cars happening
at the same time there's a very rich
audio environment in fact many times at
any given moment there might be a
hundred or more sounds being blended
together to sort of render your audio
canvas as it were some of them are so
incredibly subtly you can't pick them
out consciously but it really adds up to
a immersive kind of environment and if
you've ever watched a movie without
audio and then turned on the audio you
realize how massive and impact the audio
environment has on the experience so
it's really crucial and the Need for
Speed team in particular has won
numerous awards for years on the on the
the level of audio fidelity they have so
for the engine sounds in particular we
have a internal proprietary technology
that I can't really talk about to model
how the engine sounds as it revs through
the the range and it really the emphasis
is on engines that Rev really quickly
because you're in a racing car you want
to hear and feel your engine at
screaming through the RPM and you want
to be able to hear them the blow-off
valve goes or the turbo goes or that
exhaust note as you hit that power band
there's a lot of elements that really go
into that hmm yeah I guess that's
something that most people don't think
of I mean visually it's obviously
impressive and you you clearly realize
that rendering nice visuals is important
but for the sound I guess most people
don't I didn't think it was that
important but yeah
to no end drives the are you guys crazy
[Laughter]
yes okay another thing that goes into
games obviously is the gameplay itself
how do the well the obvious things is
you know if you think about quake how do
the opponents behave so there is this AI
thing going on is it really
AI or is it basically scripted well
that's a funny question in reality in
most games it's highly scripted and to a
lot of us that's kind of disappointing
and ten years ago or almost ten years
ago there was a lot of talk about this
what's called emergent behavior and they
wanted to have all the entities in the
game and they all wanted to have their
own behavior and so you'd get things
happening in the game sort of
spontaneously that nobody ever had ever
predicted or planned right and then the
game designers went but wait a minute
that means we can't control it all mhm
and so they sort of backed away from
that and said no we want to control the
player experience because we want this
carefully crafted really highly tuned
experience that it's very enjoyable and
so it's it's a strange dichotomy because
the the highly crafted experience is at
odds with a smarter AI mmm-hmm and so
some games really go down the AI path
and they try to have smarter algorithms
and more emergent behavior and that sort
of thing but it's at odds with the story
it's at odds with a carefully crafted
experience so there's a balance
happening there there's definitely AI
controlling there other opponent racing
cars in a racing game yeah right there
is logic in there that's working on how
best to drive around the corners we give
it a lot of hints but they aren't
simulated in the sense of you know what
you talked about before with forces and
stuff they are really scripted going
around or do they is there also a
physics simulation engine kind of
running for each of the other cars
there's absolutely a physics simulation
running for all of the opponent cars now
its varies depending on games and so
various racing games in the past in the
Need for Speed series there's been a
varying degree of
physics applied to each of them and when
you encounter traffic as an optimization
when the traffic is far away we don't
care so much but the physics of the
traffic vehicles so then they're more
scripted but when they get close or all
the opponent vehicles generally are
gonna be running the full bone physics
and in some of the games they are in
fact controlling the car the same way
the players control okay yeah we're
actually inventing the steering and the
gas and the brake inputs and the shifter
controls and then goes through the same
simulation pipeline exactly and it's
running so if you have eight cars in the
race we have eight different instances
of the physics so in case anybody ever
thought about where you're computing
power goes that's added every 18 months
according to Moore's law I guess we've
just found it it's games yes games in
flesh I guess anyway mmm impressive
games have a voracious appetite for
competing for consuming computing power
yes yes so there is also other things
that go into a game the menuing system
the online communication with other
players social media a social more
social social networks these decade
these days I suggest we don't cover that
too much because it's more or less
straightforward and we won't have a lot
of time to cover the more interesting
stuff but if you want to say something
briefly about that I mean I sort of
agree actually being in the game and
playing the game to me is the really
interesting part and it's a really
interesting computational problem that
said there's a huge amount of complexity
involved in all the social networking
and all the online on all these aspects
online is a fascinating technical
problem how do you deal with Layton sees
around with limitations in what you want
but I agree it's a huge topic worth a
huge amount of discussion but certainly
we're not gonna be able to cover it here
so so then let's move on to some of the
you know let's let's dig a little bit
deeper into how you build these games so
I guess a starting point is to realize
that these these games and the systems
they run on are actually you could call
them real-time embedded systems right
you have predefined limited resource
and I think yesterday you mentioned that
the ps3 has half a gigabyte of RAM only
the ps3 and the Xbox 360 both have 512
megabyte that's not a lot
I'm surprised so so in other words I
guess resource management is one of the
main challenges in building such a game
absolutely it's been said many times at
least internally at EA that Reis organ
development is primarily about resource
management we typically have four or
five gigabytes of data sitting on a DVD
or a blu-ray disc and somehow we have to
use it all in a machine that has
one-eighth as much memory as that and so
there's a lot of loading or streaming or
some other marshaling in the main memory
and once you get in into main memory you
have to figure out how to manage your
available CPU time and your memory
bandwidth yes do all of that within one
thirtieth or one sixtieth of a second
you know doing all these different
simulation audio rendering video
rendering sending it onto the GPU all
the stuff has to happen with them within
one let's say time slot exactly
real-time exactly and and you know it's
it's soft real-time as I say yes no one
dies because if you miss a frame it's
not the end of the world yes if you miss
a frame consistently it's gonna
seriously degrade the user experience
though so we try to maintain that in an
interesting way to look at 30 frames per
second or 60 frames per second is if
you're running at 60 frames per second
you have approximately 16 milliseconds a
little over 16 milliseconds to
accomplish everything you need to do in
that frame of the game that's you're
rendering your audio your physics your
animation taking your inputs there's a
whole lot of stuff including online and
all this other thing so that's a lot of
work to do in a very short period of
time so let's talk a little bit about
the implementation which languages do
you use mainly almost exclusively C++
okay and you do that because you like it
or because there is no alternative that
gives you that kind of performance
control on the game consoles it turns
out that there is no other alternative
really aren't any compilers probably
yeah exactly so because the the
Sony and Microsoft are providing as C++
compilers and no other compile so yeah
C++ is yeah the reason they're only
providing us those things because there
really isn't an alternative language and
that means as a practical matter all
games are written in C++ so all game
consoles provide c++ and we're stuck in
that ecosystem mhm
any yeah I guess the question is useless
done any frameworks tools you use to
make your life simpler I guess since
it's all specific to let's say the the
ps3 there aren't any frameworks or tools
that Joe programmer would know because
these are probably not available for
these platforms so you have your own
frameworks but nothing like off the
shelf we certainly within EA because
it's a large company we have quite a few
frameworks of our own we also license
frameworks EA in places has used the
havok physic's engine for example that i
mentioned earlier and if you go and look
in the industry literature there are
various other middleware packages that
you know EA may or may not use but other
game developers in you
I guess one one we will talk about
design patterns or architectural
patterns later but one as far as I know
one key building block in the way you
build your systems is that you do
implement the engines in C++ but then
the actual the scripting of opponents
the actual design of how things look
this is done in in separate data driven
styles right so you did you don't want
to change the C++ code if you want to
change some parameters of how your
opponent drives yeah absolutely so many
systems are at a minimum parametrized
heavily and that sort of scales up to
fully data-driven systems and then in
the extreme we get all the way up to
scripting languages so in the game
industry a very common language to embed
in a game engine is Lua for example
about it I was actually planning to do
an episode about that for years but
never got allowed to do it it is an
excellent language because it embeds
very very well and it's performance is
reasonable we carefully control the
scope of what we use it for right very
very specific tasks that aren't
performance intensive have you ever
thought about using domain-specific
languages that you build specifically
for your kinds of use cases I mean one
key challenge we'll talk about it in a
minute is parallelism and I'm not sure
whether Lua has a lot of very useful
abstractions for that maybe it might
happen in the C++ world but that same
statement is true C++ is not very good
for parallel stuff have you thought
about doing domain-specific languages
where you maybe even be able to let's
say flexibly switch between generating
C++ which is fast but inflexible and
running it in an interpreted way which
is flexible but slow absolutely and over
the last decade or two what has happened
is as systems become more and more
data-driven
they've eventually gotten to the point
where we belatedly realized that they
are essentially domain-specific
languages they become data that drives
the C++ engine but they are a limited
language that are not a turing-complete
by any stretch but they are a DSL
effectively but we got there in Reverse
right we if we just progressively
parameterised it until hey guess what
we're almost at a language rarely do we
start at the language side and design
backwards we've done that for game play
languages on occasion sometimes we use
Lua but other times we have internal
languages that are purpose-built for
that kind of thing because maybe we
don't have one I have that much
generality or we want to figure out how
to make it perform better than the
generic Lua for example and certainly it
has been a topic internally about can we
do any better
can we get performance improvements like
rather than you know Louis slow and so
try to avoid using it only using in
strategic places can we actually turn
around and create a DSL that gives us a
performance win I have yet to see that
happen in practice but actually the
second talk that I gave this morning was
essentially about that topic okay
and I believe it has much broader
implications to the computing industry
in general I'm asking for two reasons
one is that my own area of
expertise and work is the main specific
languages so I'm always interested in
that the other thing is yesterday
morning I interviewed Martino turski who
does Scala and he just on a research
grant for developing domain-specific
languages for really domain-specific
concurrency in parallelism as Scala
embedded dsls so this topic about dsls
and higher levels of abstraction and
more clever libraries and translation
engines is clearly something that that's
on the on the rise and so I was just
curious yeah and I'm actually a big
proponent of that and at the end of my
talk this morning somebody actually
specifically asked about Scala and its
ability to or its framework that it
provides in order to build dia cells
within it yeah I mean they are good I
mean kind of off topic here but Oh
turkey told me that they are actually
going as far as not running the embedded
DSL that are embedded in Scala as Scala
programs but these deals else just build
a syntax tree and then they have a
compiler to CUDA or to C to really build
completely separate programs well that's
very interesting to hear because this
morning I was suggesting that they
should generate open CL yes and EA is in
fact a member of the open CL Standards
Committee and this is a cross-platform
platform that I believe we can target
and it presents a tasking model similar
to one of the design patterns that we've
adopted within EA okay I guess we should
put this to the discussion when we shut
down the podcast here so we you two
thought you talked about concurrency
already so I guess one of the central
challenges of what you're doing is
multi-core not just I mean if you
writing a PC game you have multicores
in the in the CPU but I guess these GPUs
are highly parallel parallelized already
so any how do you deal with that so
we've been dealing it with it since the
late 90s when GPUs first started to
appear on the scene and the first step
was let's just offload the actual
rendering so back in the mid-90s we were
actually rendering every single pixel as
CPU could but when Hardware started to
become available
that would do it for us that hardware
now started to become able to run
asynchronously and that means the CPU
sets up the work hands it over to the
GPU and now you have two processes
happening in parallel now that's not the
conventional multi-core model but it
definitely gets things happening
asynchronously and you start having to
figure out how to partition the work
effectively the arrival of the
PlayStation 3 in the Xbox 360 was a bit
of a shock to the system for us because
all of a sudden we were confronted with
our primary market the machines in the
primary market having three or six or
eight Hardware threads so you had to
parallelize existing code I guess you
didn't rewrite everything well it turns
out paralyzing existing code it's really
hard yeah and and so in practice what we
do is we find pieces of a game engine
and we extract them out turn them into
tasks and one of the design patterns
that we've adopted is a we call it job
manager within EA but often it's called
a task graph for a task manager and what
you do is you define a specific piece of
a program a kernel a computational
kernel if you will and then you schedule
that to run on other processors right so
your mainline code decides there's a
bunch of work that has to be done puts
it in a queue to get done and then the
work processors such as the SPU's that
are found in the Cell processor in the
PlayStation 3 are constantly pulling
work off of those queues and then you
just have to manage that the queue
doesn't get too big and stays unreal
limited then you know that it's actually
that's right and then sometimes you have
to pick up the results as they come back
although some tasks just go to the GPU
and they never actually come back to the
CPU another design pattern since we're
already talking about it you mentioned
yesterday are these vector-based
interfaces so if I get it correctly you
can't let me know if I do or if I don't
instead of saying here's an object I
call a method you say here is a bunch of
objects I want the following method to
be executed on each of them and then
some lower-level can find out whether
there is only one core or thread to do
it sequentially or several do
parallel that kind of ride that's kind
of right part of the problem we're
trying to solve here is you don't just
get currency from having multiple
processors individual processors
individual threads Hardware threads have
concurrency within them some of that
shows up as sim D instructions some of
it just shows up as pipelining and
overlapping instructions and concurrent
memory accesses so there's all these
different elements of parallelism and
when I talk about it I tend to use the
label vectorization when you're going to
optimize for this kind of concurrency
that's at the instruction level I just
lump that into it and call it
vectorization and so when you take an
algorithm and you vectorize you're
trying to take advantage of all the
concurrency that you can get at the
instruction level at the memory
organization level simultaneous
transactions on the bus because things
can overlap on the memory bus and that
kind of thing once you get all that
sorted out we find that many algorithms
data parallel algorithms at least we can
get a 10times performance speed-up by
doing that sort of optimization the
problem is if you haven't designed your
software to do a lot of the same
calculation that the same kind of
objects all at once in a batch you can't
apply those sort of realizations so if
an example I use all the time is culling
which is essentially the process of
deciding what to draw and not to draw so
if you have thousands of things to draw
but you can only afford to draw a few
hundred you have to quickly toss out
toss away the things that don't need to
be drawn because they're not in the view
framework that process can be quite
expensive and if you walk through your
graph of objects and as you hit each
object you say Oh
call your cul method to see if you're
visible or not then it goes through this
college and eventually it says what's
the view frustum what's my bounding box
do the calculation to see if it's
visible if you do that thousands and
thousands of times at 60 frames per
second you find you quickly use up all
your CPU weight 18 months to get a
faster one yeah and we just don't have
that option
and in fact single processors aren't
getting much faster and also the game
consoles haven't been you know changed
much in the last six or seven years
anyway I mean the Microsoft Xbox is ages
old I think yeah so I mean our console
generations last six to ten years
however they last and so we have to get
faster and faster on a given machine and
that means that what you really need to
do is you need to identify the large
pieces of work and you need to batch up
the calculation and once you have it all
as instead of going through a thousand
objects and individually calling them
what you want to do is you want to have
a thousand of bounding boxes all at once
and then you can write one
high-performance algorithm that all at
once does a thousand bounding boxes or
whatever your calculation that does
destroy the object-oriented purity of
your object model a little bit because
you have to you know define different
kinds of interfaces absolutely and not
just a little bit but I can I can
completely derail if you're
object-oriented design another challenge
I imagine you mentioned ps3 Xbox PCs how
do you get the platform independence is
C++ good enough to kind of transparently
do that or also I mean I guess the the
parallel nature I mean some have several
course out of stoned so you have to even
have different ways of parallelizing
things depending on the platform how do
you handle that this is where the 80/20
rule comes to the rescue so that the the
basic rule of thumb is 80% of your
performance happens in 20% of your code
that means the other 80% of the code
isn't especially performance intensive
right so you write it in C++ you try to
make sure you don't do anything platform
specific and for the most part it ports
pretty well to all the games and maybe
you provide a layer of like micro have
portable libraries the high differences
between file systems and memory
management and all that sort of stuff
that 20% that's performance intensive
typically you're going to do different
versions for every platform okay and
there might be some tools that help us
stay agnostic to the platform but yeah
there's going to be a fair bit of
of machine-specific tuning and of course
all the stuff you do with your DSL and
data-driven kind of stuff is obviously
platform-independent anyway so that's
not a big deal
well the implementation of the DSL of
that switch at all it may be tuned for
every platform yes yeah hmm so let's
look at a couple of more of these
patterns you've found or implemented or
refused and I guess one pattern you I
think didn't explicitly mention
yesterday but which I kind of it jumped
like into my eyes
this whole rendering pipeline kind of
thing is obviously pipes and filters
right I mean this is just one step
create something that's piped to the
next filter or stage which is then piped
to the next one right well you would
think okay see I love it so different
rendering engines take a different
approach to these things but generally
the rendering is broken down into you're
rendering different surfaces so for
example you might render a environment
map and what that really is is it's a
separate rendering of the world from the
point of view of being inside a shiny
object a car for example so you you
choose a wide-angle lens and you render
the world in a low resolution of detail
so now you have this picture of this of
the world that's around the car and then
once that's rendered you use it as a
texture that you then feed into a later
rendering pass when you're actually
going to draw the car that the user is
going to see and you use that reflection
in your pixel shaders to reflect the
world so that so when you're looking at
the car you can actually see the
buildings that are going by and if the
car look like it's in the world and so
it's kind of like piping from one stage
to the other but it's not actually done
using that sort of terminology or that
sort of mechanism in the in any
rendering engine I've seen so then I
guess we should look at some of the
patterns you do use and it's easy for me
to name those because they were on your
slides one of them was the sim
simulation presentation split that
like motor view controller it is quite
similar to model view controller you
have the simulation and it's essentially
updating the game state and so you run
the simulation for one frame and now you
have in some form another sitting in
memory maybe spread throughout memory
but you have this state of your
simulation world and the job of the
presentation is to render that both
audio and graphically and the force
feedback on the controller so games that
are using this pattern we've discovered
have a fairly formal split between those
two halves and they try to carefully
control the data that passes between
them so that this data can be captured
can be used for a replay for example
plus because the two are decoupled like
that once the simulation finish it's
doing its calculation it hands this nice
little package of data over to
presentation and then it can because the
program is concurrent on multiple
threads the simulation can carry on with
the next frame and says you're
overlapping the calculation of the next
frame with the rendering of the current
frame and you get parallelism at a
coarse grain level and everybody's busy
all the time
exactly another one you mentioned is
services I don't remember what it was
actually yeah so services are like an
animation service or a rendering service
or an audio service and so they're
essentially just Singleton's in the
program they are factories for managing
the kind of objects that you would have
in any given subsystem so that you know
the physics service manages rigid bodies
for example okay another one is the
data-driven system stuff which we
already talked about yep we already
talked about top manager and vector
based interfaces yeah the last one I
wrote down was the pre-baked data yeah
the key here is any computation that you
don't have to do while the game is
running is a computation you don't have
to do well the game is running it's a
pretty simple concept yes so basically
it says if we can pre calculate stuff
and my favorite example here is lighting
information so a lot of games have
fairly intricate lighting and sometimes
the
the calculations that go into lighting
can be very very intensive one of our
games the lighting calculation to light
the entire world would run for three
days on high-end pcs so you can't do
that in real time on any machine much
less on a $500 game console or $300 now
because they've all come down in price
but so what we do is we pre calculate at
all we store it in highly optimized data
structures and then we bring in and off
of disk and we feed that pre calculated
data to them the rendering engines it's
not all completely can there's still
some dynamic calculations happening
based on that but the idea is get your
data into exactly the form that the game
machine needs it rather than a more
generalized form and an extreme example
of that is we often pre-baked data to
the point where we can literally take
the file that's sitting on disk copy it
into memory and begin using it
immediately
there's no serialization or
deserializing direct memory image direct
memory image sitting on the disk and
sometimes there's a bit of tweaking we
want to do fixing up pointers and that
sort of thing but by and large the
closer we can get it to the memory
resident image the better because then
you just issue a read to the disk
operating system delivers the block of
whatever megabytes and you get a pointer
to the beginning of it and quite often
you can just pass that straight to the
GPU and it starts drawing one thing you
showed yesterday is also the the
skateboard guy driving around on his
skateboard yep and I wonder how the
movements actually I'm kind of diverting
back to them you know it's a simulation
thing here how the the guy who rides the
skateboard is rendered is that described
algorithmically or do you use motion
capture or something like that so first
of all what do you mean by rendered
wrong word finding out how he moves
simulate right okay so in skate it was a
combination of pre-recorded motion
captured animation so motion capture is
a process whereby you get an actual
human actor you put him in a funny black
suit with white markers all over him and
then you have special cameras that track
those white markers and he goes and he
does the moves so we have a motion
capture studio at EA in Vancouver and
we've had all sorts of football players
and American football players and
baseball players and golfers I think we
had Tiger Woods in once a while back and
skateboarding we had the skateboarders
and they come in and they they do the
various moves that we want to represent
in the game we have cameras from all
sorts of angles and we capture the data
and a whole bunch of software does a lot
of pre-processing and it turns it into
3d data then we take that animation data
and we build up a database and in the
game when a player wants to run in a
straight line and then turn right we go
and look in the database and we find run
in a straight line and we find turn
right and we can play these things back
and then there's all sorts of techniques
to blend from one animation to another
and combine them in different ways so
maybe his legs are running in his upper
body's doing something different like
shooting a gun in the demo yesterday it
looked pretty good although I thought it
was a little bit too fast if that's the
right word it it's it seemed to me as if
the bodies that moved weren't massive
enough you know some of the how was the
word tracker in German inertia right it
felt like that was a little bit it felt
like was a bit a little bit too light
somehow I don't know you know what I'm
talking about yeah I do and it's a
really finicky tuning issue yes when
building games because you want to have
fast action and very rapid response to
to user input but there's a trade-off if
it's too fast then it feels like it's
too light or too many verbal and and so
there is a real gameplay balance going
one of these realistic versus funny or
fun exactly right okay
so let's briefly talk about the process
you use to develop these games I mean
it's probably a couple dozens of people
at least involved in this game and I
guess you also have like stakeholders
who are not programmers like
and and and and and things like that or
people like that I imagine those being
quite interesting as customers from a
programmers perspective yeah it makes
for very interesting and dynamic teams
and it's a hugely creative and
productive environment I have a hard
time imagining and what a team of just
software engineers is like after
spending so long in the game business
because as a group software engineers
are typically quite left brained and
they're very logical and methodical and
you would hope so at least
you would hope so artists on the other
hand are much more right brain they're
much more holistic and visual and their
approach to problems is very very
different and you bring these groups of
people together and at times they clash
they just don't understand each other
but once you get a team that is meshed
together and working effectively it's
intensely creative because these the
complementary skill sets and so it's a
it's a great environment for the games
we've been talking about the team sizes
are typically anything from 20 to 50
engineers or 20 to 60 engineers at least
that many artists modern games for the
PlayStation 3 and Xbox 360 are extremely
content heavy so the the amount like a
movie already almost absolutely and the
amount of people you need to build all
that content I mean you know every
single building you see next the
racetrack the racetrack itself all this
data all the the textures that go on the
polygonal models all of this stuff has
to be created out of essentially whole
cloth and that just takes a really large
team and then you have animators who are
responsible for tuning the animations
that come out of the motion capture
studio you have the people in the motion
capture studio you have our audio people
that are generating the sound effects
like the skateboard going across the
sidewalk or the engine sounds and you
have guys that go out and record the
sounds of actual car engines and they
have all sorts of stories about you know
flying over to Europe and going into
Ferrari and getting sounds of the latest
and greatest engines
that's lucky guys I wish I could go but
so there's all different parts of the
team and so I think at the largest Need
for Speed team I saw it was approaching
200 people and it defense depends on
where you define the boundary so if you
include marketing people and earn and
all sorts of others it can be quite
large so I guess then did the
distinction between the engine in C++
and the data-driven higher level stuff
and maybe the runtime tunable parameters
is also a way to decouple these kinds of
people at least a little bit so you
don't have to have the C++ programmer
involved whenever the artist says you
know this guy needs to move a little bit
faster or a little bit slower or
something sometimes I wish we were more
decoupled but yes absolutely the reason
that you want to expose those parameters
is because the key to building a good
game is rapid iteration because what
there's no magic formula that makes a
great game and what you want to be able
to do is try things rapidly and by
trying things rapidly that means you get
to experiment with what works better and
so there's a rule of thumb that
basically says the more times you can
iterate the better and that means
speeding up the iteration time as a
programmer think about it as your
compile link yet run cycle the faster
that is the more times you can you can
find in in fix bugs and you can refine
your code and make it perform better
it's the same thing with game design
you're going and you can refine the art
and the gameplay and all the different
aspects so by exposing tunable
parameters
especially those tunable parameters
which can be done during gameplay like
ideally while the guy is driving the car
around
he can be changing the coefficient of
friction on the tires so he gets the
right feel of it right if he can just
keep driving around the track and he
never has to quit the game and rebuild
and redeploy right you don't want to do
any of that stuff cuz it can take a very
long time so ideally while the game is
running against we call those parameters
and get just perfect so we have to leave
this room in about five minutes so I
never almost through anyway okay so I'm
last question how do you think will
games look in five or ten years
I mean it's obvious obviously a question
you get a lot of many times but still I
mean what do you think except of course
you know frame work frame rail frame
rate will get hired level of detail will
get higher is there any fundamental
change coming or is it just going to be
everything is better 500 different
sounds so first of all I don't know that
I agree with that okay
frame rate at 30 or 60 there's not
really much reason why okay so we're
pretty much at this point resolution
might go higher but really we're aiming
at HDTVs we don't expect to see a lot of
resolution increases there so there will
be some increase in fidelity but we've
already hit a point of diminishing
returns right we're at a point where if
you double the computational power we
can throw at the graphics we haven't
made it look twice as good in fact this
last generation was a bit of a struggle
for us because we're at that point of
diminishing returns yeah they do look
better yeah they are in higher res but
what's the next generation going to
include and my speculation is we're
gonna see the differences in behavior
it's going to move better it's going to
do things smarter it's going to behave
in more believable ways and that's gonna
be a challenge because it's easy to sell
graphics right right you can show a
screenshot say look how much better that
looks but behavior you can't show
screenshots and it's a more subtle
effect so I think it will lead to better
gameplay but it's gonna be a hard it's
gonna be a hard story to sell to the
consumer mm-hmm why what's the
improvement you can do 3d games you know
I mean really the PD with the glasses
and stuff and our games are doing 3d and
and you know performance improvements
will help there because essentially you
have to render the scene twice right so
exactly okay I think we're through
anything else you want to say you know
like famous last words at the end I've
had a great time in Munich this is a
beautiful city and I've very happy to
have had a chance to visit good great
and I'm happy to have had you or going
to have you on se radio it was a very
nice conversation Thanks
thank you
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio as a radio is an
educational program brought to you by
hillside Europe if you want more
information about the podcast and the
other episodes visit our website at se -
radio dotnet if you want to support us
you can donate to the SA radio team via
the website or you can advertise for SA
radio for example by clicking on the
Digg reddit delicious and Slashdot
buttons or by talking about us on
Twitter and Facebook you can also
support us by joining team and
shouldering some of the work to contact
the team please send email to team at se
- radio net or if your feedback is
specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of se radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under a
creative commons 2.5 license please see
the website for details
[Music]